Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Norman H. Strouse Papers, 1852-1990 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Norman H. Strouse papers 1852-1990 and undated
J. Walter Thompson Company.
17.3 linear feet Extent: 13000 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Norman Hulbert Strouse served as Chairman and Chief Executive Officer of JWT during the 1960s. He was also a noted bibliophile and private publisher. The papers of Norman H. Strouse span the years 1852 to 1990, with the bulk of material dating from the 1950s to the 1960s. Records consist of correspondence, office files and memoranda, reports, writings and speeches, charts, client presentations, notes and notebooks, publications, clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks. The collection primarily documents Strouse's work in the JWT Detroit Office; other files touch on corporate administration for the entire company; company history; and public relations. Major clients include Ford, Kraft foods, and Scott paper products. The collection also partially documents Strouse's interests as a bibliophile: book collecting; the works of Robert Louis Stevenson; and his involvement with Silverado Press.
RL.00751
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Norman H. Strouse Papers were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from the J. Walter Thompson Company in 1987.
Biographical Note
1906 Nov. 4 Born Norman Hulbert Strouse, Olympia, Washington
1925-1928 Advertising Department, Post-Intelligencer, Seattle, Washington
1929-1936 Space buyer, J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) San Francisco Office
1936-1941 Account Representative, JWT San Francisco Office
1942 Account Supervisor and Assistant Pacific Coast Manager, JWT San Francisco Office
1942-1945 Army Air Force; Executive Officer of Information and Education, Special Staff Section in the Pacific
1946-1947 Account Supervisor, Ford Motor Company account, JWT Detroit Office
1946 Aug. 2 Married Charlotte A. Holt
1947 Elected Vice President, JWT
1948-1955 Manager, JWT Detroit Office
1952 Elected Director, JWT
1955 Elected President, JWT
1960-1967 Elected Chief Executive Officer, JWT
1964-1968 Elected Chairman of the Board, JWT
1968 Retired from the J. Walter Thompson Company
1993 Jan. 19 Died, St. Helena, Calif.
Norman H. Strouse was a member of the following advertising and marketing organizations: the American Association of Advertising Agencies, Chairman of the Board (1964-1965); the Marketing Science Institute, Trustee (1962-); and the National Outdoor Advertising Bureau, Director and Board Chairman (1964-1965).
Library or bibliographic-related organizations with which he was involved include: the Bibliographical Society; the Book Club of California, Board Member; the Friends of the Columbia Library, Advisory Council (1963-); the Grolier Club, Council Member (1961-); the Manuscript Society; the National Book Committee, Chairman (1962-1964); the National Library Week Steering Committee (1958-1963); and the New York Public Library, Trustee (1963-).
For further biographical information, see the Biographical Information series of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives.
Collection Overview
The papers of Norman H. Strouse span the years 1852 to 1990, with the bulk of material dating from the 1950s to the 1960s. Records consist of correspondence, office files and memoranda, reports, writings and speeches, charts, client presentations, notes and notebooks, publications, clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks. The collection primarily documents Strouse's work in the JWT Detroit Office; other files touch on corporate administration for the entire company; company history; and public relations. Major clients include Ford, Kraft foods, and Scott paper products. The collection also partially documents Strouse's interests as a bibliophile: book collecting; the works of Robert Louis Stevenson; and his involvement with Silverado Press.
Collection is arranged into six series: General JWT Office Files; Professional Associations; Business Writings and Speeches; Book Collecting, Library and Printing Interests; Personal Materials; and Oversize Materials.
Subject Headings
Strouse, Norman H.; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office; Ford Motor Company; Kraft Foods Company; Scott Paper Company; Stevenson, Robert Louis, 1850-1894; Silverado Press; Advertising -- Automobiles -- United States; Advertising agencies -- Michigan -- Detroit; Advertising agencies -- New York (State) -- New York; Advertising -- Management; Advertising executives; Book collectors -- United States; Advertising campaigns; Clippings; Photographs; Scrapbooks; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- General JWT Office Files, 1886-1989 and undated, 9 Boxes
  Includes materials relating to general corporate administration, management, and corporate history. Arranged into four subseries: Clippings and Photographs; Company History; Corporate Administration; and Correspondence.
  Clippings and Photographs consist of newspaper and magazine articles from both domestic and foreign newspapers and magazines as well as photographs, correspondence, newsletters, and telegrams that pertain to the articles, including from Strouse's period at the Detroit Office. Includes materials on outdoor advertising campaigns. Arranged chronologically. Additional items in oversize boxes.
  Company History contains correspondence, memoranda, transcripts, writings and a report, related to the history of JWT. Colin Dawkins, a writer for the J. Walter Thompson Company, collected information for a history of the company. This subseries contains the correspondence between Dawkins and Strouse in regard to Dawkins's research. The correspondence includes general information about JWT, especially management, as well as information specifically about Strouse's experiences in the company. The subseries includes copies of some early company correspondence, including: J. Walter Thompson's resignation; letters from Stanley Resor to JWT employees Rae H. Smith and Loyd R. Coleman; and to E.J. Copeland of Nash Motors regarding Kelvinator. There is a commentary by Lewis Mumford concerning the company library for employees, begun by Helen Lansdowne Resor. Some correspondence refers to materials in the Detroit Series, Ford Motor Company Subseries; and the Corporate Administration Series. Basic Roots of the J. Walter Thompson Company is an historical overview of the company compiled by Vice President Howard Henderson. It describes JWT's driving principles and policies and compares it with other agencies, including their standings in worldwide competition. Basic Roots also includes case histories of some company clients and their products for the period from about 1904 to the 1920s. Items are arranged by type of material, then chronologically. The transcripts are restricted until written permission from the interviewee's heirs is obtained. See also in the JWT Archives: Colin Dawkins Papers, Howard Henderson Papers, and Charles Raymond's memoir in the Company History and Reminiscences Collection.
  Corporate Administration consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, billing and organizational charts, notebooks, clippings, and scrapbooks, and includes information on general management concerns and decisions regarding staff, including assignments and compensation; operating expenses; and the succession of top management positions in the 1950s. The subseries documents Mr. Strouse's transition to the presidency and the management reorganization of the New York office, including the establishment of the Executive Team, the Administrative Committee, the Operations Committee, and the Review Boards. Documentation of personnel policy issues is scattered throughout the subseries, especially in regard to upper levels of management. There are also descriptions of the responsibilities of various positions and the professional relationships between various JWT staff members. Strouse wrote numerous memoranda evaluating the course of management policies and changes as well as future prospects for change, including those that would occur as a result of retirements. Memoranda on various aspects of forward planning are scattered throughout the series. Also includes information on the acquisition of new clients and the satisfaction of current clients, trends in advertising, billings, profits, and stock holdings. Contains information about other advertising companies, including comparisons of total billings, market distributions, and evaluation of staff who were under consideration for recruitment to JWT. The Company Image folder includes information on the architectural and interior design of the New York offices as well as discussions of the impressions of the company held by other companies and the public. Materials on public relations document responses to two articles by Arno H. Johnson of the JWT Research Department and a third article, The Best Advertisements from Reader's Digest, 1955-1961, which Strouse had mailed to members of Congress and other federal government officials and some corporate leaders. Arranged with correspondence and memoranda at the beginning, followed by topical files in alphabetical order, and then further divided into Writings and Speeches and Clippings. All folders are arranged chronologically therein. See also Oversize Materials.
  Correspondence includes general correspondence files relating to both Norman Strouse's business and private dealings, and documents general management issues; responses to promotions and retirements; and Strouse's visits to international offices. Primarily consists of Strouse's reading files of letters and memoranda written to executives of various JWT offices, business colleagues, friends, and other associates. Some files, though containing mostly correspondence, also contain clippings, brochures and other materials concerned with the issues discussed in the correspondence. Strouse's personal letters in this series detail his serious interest in books, book collecting and printing. All of the correspondence dating after Strouse's retirement in 1968 is personal. Arranged chronologically. See also Oversize Materials.
  Some items have a reference to a numbered letter (e.g., letter #9); these numbers refer to letters in the J. Walter Thompson Company History subseries. Arranged by type of material, then subject. See also Oversize Materials.
  - Clippings and Photographs, 1930-1984 and undated
    - Adman with a Difference, Business Week, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Advertising: The Visible Persuaders, Time, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Association of Newspaper Classified Advertising Managers' Prominent Citizen Award, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Broadcast: color television, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Broadcast: Kraft's international commercial telecast, 1965 (Box 1)
    - JWT Centennial, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Office, 1930-1979 and undated
      - 1948-1951 and undated (Box 1)
      - 1930-1979 and undated (Box 1)
      - Photographs, ca. 1940s, 1953, 1955 and undated
        - (Includes photographs of Baby Talk billboard campaign.) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1984 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Press, 1936-1968 (Box 1)
  - Company History, 1886-1979 and undated
    - Background information, 1931-1964 (Box 1)
    - Bookmark to promote JWT, ca. 1886 (Box 1)
    - Copy of original certificate of incorporation of JWT, 1896 (Box 1)
    - Early JWT correspondence, 1916
      - (Includes 1916 letter from J. Walter Thompson to Board of Directors.) (Box 1)
    - Getting on in Advertising, by Charles Raymond, ca. 1930s (Box 1)
    - Norman Strouse interview by Sidney Bernstein, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Norman Strouse telephone interview, 1979 (Box 2)
    - San Francisco, JWT representative information for Newspaper Publishers Committee, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Some Basic Roots of the J. Walter Thompson Company by Howard Henderson, 1959, (2 folders)
      - (Clients: Krohn, Fechheimer and Company/Red Cross Shoes, Breneman/Brenlin Window Shades, Andrew Jergens Company/Woodbury's Fine Facial Soap, Arbuckle Brothers Company/Yuban Coffee, Pond's Extract Company/Pond's Creams, and Lever Brothers/Lux) (Box 2)
  - Corporate Administration, 1945-1979 and undated
    - Company image, 1946-1969, undated (Box 2)
      [Includes information on the architectural and interior design of the New York Offices as well as discussions of the impressions of the company held by other companeis and the public.]
    - Contents of an album to commemorate Norman Strouse's becoming president of JWT, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Contents of an album to commemorate the election of Dan Seymour as president and Norman Strouse as CEO and chairman of the board, 1964 (Box 2)
    - European trip, Kraft, 1963, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Finance, 1945-1965, undated (Box 2)
    - Forward planning, 1962-1967 (Box 3)
      [Clients: P. Ballentine and Sons/"Mitch Miller Show," Nestle's Milk Products/Nescafe, and Seven-Up]
    - Management planning (notebook), 1960-1967 (Box 3)
    - Management transition, 1959-1979, undated (Box 3)
    - Organization, 1955-1964 and undated (Box 3)
    - Personnel file, 1954-1968, undated (Box 3)
    - Planning for the Presidency, 1955 (Box 3)
      [Clients: E.F. Hutton and Co. and Scott Paper Co./Father Knows Best]
    - Puerto Rico trip, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Reference notebook: personal, 1955-1966 (Box 3)
    - Resolutions by the Board of Directors concerning Peggy King and Samuel Meek, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Shareholder file, 1962-1969 (Box 3)
    - Speech by Dan Seymour for Norman Strouse's birthday, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1916-1989 and undated
    - General (Box 3)
      - 1936-1964 (Box 3)
      - 1955-1967 (Box 3)
      - 1964 Jan.-Dec., (6 folders) (Box 4)
      - 1965 Jan.-Dec. (Box 4)
      - 1965 Jan.-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 5)
      - 1966 Jan.-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - 1966 Jan.-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 6)
      - 1967 Jan.-Sept., (4 folders) (Box 6)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 7)
      - 1970-1989 and undated (Box 7)
    - Business Week cover story, 1960 (Box 7)
    - Client file, 1955-1960s, undated (Box 7)
      [Clients: Eastman-Kodak, Ford Motor Co., Kraft, Lever Brothers, Pan American, Standard Brands, Scott Paper Co., Seven-Up, and Quaker Oats]
    - Colin Dawkins, 1916-1981, undated (Box 7)
      [Client: Nash Motors/Kelvinator]
    - Colin Dawkins, Resor Library, 1928 and 1979 (Box 7)
    - Detroit Office files, 1930-1954
      Includes correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, client presentations and speeches, clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks. These materials primarily document various aspects of the Ford Motor Company account with the JWT and, to a lesser extent, Strouse's personal relationships with members of Ford management. The client presentations, including some to Henry Ford II, include analyses of expenditures and annual budgets, sales and marketing figures, and the results of a study authorized by the Ford Motor Company. Outdoor billboard advertising was an important component of the Ford account, and Norman Strouse was an innovator in this type of advertising. The Baby Talk billboard developed for the Ford Motor Company Campaign of 1947 is well documented in the subseries. There are comments from Ford dealers and district managers, outdoor advertising companies, and other J. Walter Thompson Company offices about the campaign. These groups also submitted, to the J. Walter Thompson Company Detroit office, additional solicited and unsolicited comments which they had received from the public or found in newspapers. The Baby Talk Billboard Scrapbook, a portfolio presentation album assembled by General Outdoor Advertising for Norman Strouse, also documents the campaign, including the public's response.
      - General, 1948-1979 (Box 7)
      - Ford Motor Company
        - General, 1949-1979 (Box 7)
        - Direct mail advertising, 1953 (Box 7)
        - Outdoor, Baby Talk billboard, 1947, (3 folders) (Box 7)
        - Personal, congratulatory letters, 1955 (Box 7)
    - Financial, 1960-1964 (Box 8)
    - JWT, 1978-1988, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - JWT archives, 1979-1987 (Box 8)
    - Letters and clippings in regard to Strouse's speech Velocity is the New Dimension, 1956
      - See Personal Series Business Talks v. 2 for speech (Box 8)
    - Memoranda, 1949-1968, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Public relations, A-Z, 1962-1963 (Box 9)
- Professional Associations Series, 1956-1978 and undated, 3 Boxes
  Contains correspondence, photographs, brochures and publications pertaining to Strouse's involvement in organizations including the AAAA, panels on which he served, award ceremonies and honorary dinners he attended. See also Oversize Materials. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Advertising Club of New York, 1958 (Box 9)
  - American Red Cross, New York Chapter
    - General, 1962 (Box 9)
    - Annual meeting, 1963 (Box 9)
    - New headquarters dedication, 1963, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - B'nai B'rith dinner for Arjay Miller, 1968 June (Box 9)
  - Economic Club of New York meeting
    - Election of Strouse as president, 1966 (Box 9)
    - 1966 November meeting (Box 9)
    - 1967 Jan.-Apr., (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Honorary Doctor of Laws, Colgate University, 1958 (Box 10)
  - Joint Defense Appeal
    - Dinner, 1957 (Box 10)
    - Awards, 1958 (Box 10)
  - National Outdoor Advertising Bureau, 1958 (Box 10)
  - Nikita Krushchev's visit, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Printer's Ink Awards jury, 1958 (Box 10)
  - San Francisco Advertising Club
    - Honorary Chairman, 1978 (Box 10)
    - No News Is Bad News, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Time's 40th anniversary dinner, 1963 May (Box 10)
- Business Writings and Speeches Series, 1935-1968 and undated, 10 Boxes
  Includes the writings and speeches given by Norman Strouse during his time at the JWT San Francisco, New York and Detroit offices. Also included are correspondence, photographs, press releases, programs, articles, clippings, drafts, JWT newsletters, brochures, pamphlets and invitations associated with various speeches or writings. The speeches concern advertising, current affairs and management. The December 1961 Common Market speech contains extensive background research materials on the European community. Strouse expressed his views on women in the workplace in a speech to the Women's Ad Club of New York in 1959, mentioning his own career beginnings as a secretary. The Advertising Gold Medal Award file contians a letter from Lyndon B. Johnson to Strouse congratulating him on winning the 1965 award.
  Organized into five categories: American Asscociation of Advertising Agencies; Bound volumes; General business talks; Detroit Office; and San Francisco Office. Arranged chronologically. See also Personal Series.
  - American Association of Advertising Agencies
    - 1956, Our Explosive Personnel Requirements During the Next Decade, 38th Annual Meeting (Box 10)
    - 1960, Madison Avenue Is Many Places, Regional Council Meetings, Chicago and Coronado (Box 10)
    - 1961, Western Region Convention opening statement (Box 10)
    - 1962, Special Problems of Advertising Agency Management in the U.S. Today, Second International Meeting (Box 10)
    - 1964 and undated, Strouse's election as chairman of AAAA at annual meeting (Box 10)
    - 1964, Address to Institute of Advanced Advertising Studies (Box 11)
    - 1964, Growing Threat to Creativity, Western Regional Convention (Box 11)
    - 1964, Personnel Projections Revisited, Eastern Regional Council Annual Meeting (Box 11)
    - 1965, Right to Be Heard, Michigan Council Annual Meeting (Box 11)
    - 1965, Operating Committee meeting, Rocky Mountain Council (Box 11)
    - 1965, Annual meeting, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1965, Eastern Conference luncheon (Box 11)
    - 1967, How's Your Green Thumb Today, 50th Annual Convention (Box 11)
  - Bound Volumes
    - Vol. I, 1950-1955 and undated (Box 12)
      - Population of the U.S., undated (Box 12)
      - Attitude of Staff Officers, undated (Box 12)
      - Small Town Press as a Preservative in American Life, 1950 (Box 12)
      - Necessity of Contacting Local Distributors and Dealers, 1951 (Box 12)
      - Georgia Press Association address, 1952 (Box 12)
      - National Convention of Outdoor Advertising Association address, 1953 (Box 12)
      - Annual Convention of International Electrotypers & Stereotypers Association, 1953 (Box 12)
      - Annual Convention of Allied Daily Newspapers of Washington address, 1955 (Box 12)
      - Wayne County Republican Women's Finance Committee, 1955 (Box 12)
      - Anheuser-Busch presentation notes, 1955 (Box 12)
      - FDAF committee chairmen's meeting remarks, 1955 (Box 12)
      - Testimonial luncheon talks response, Adcraft Club of Detroit, 1955 (Box 12)
      - Presentation introduction, Minnesota Mining & Manufacturing Company, 1955 (Box 12)
    - Vol. II, 1956
      - What Is Your Newspaper's Target for 1965?, Annual Convention of Newspaper Advertising Executives Association (Box 12)
      - Role of Advertising in our American Society, Shell Management Course Arden House (Box 12)
      - Our Explosive Personnel Requirements During the Next Decade, Annual Meeting of AAAA (Box 12)
      - Triptych for Advertising in the West, Annual Convention of Advertising Association of the West (Box 12)
      - Advertising with a Capital "A" and an International Accent, Ford International Sales Managers (Box 12)
      - Talk before field representatives (Box 12)
      - Velocity Is the New Dimension, Annual Meeting of Audit Bureau of Circulations Chicago (Box 12)
      - Velocity Is Your Challenge, Annual Convention of Outdoor Advertising Association of America (Box 12)
    - Vol. III, 1957
      - Annual Meeting of Sales Organization, Minneapolis Star & Tribune (Box 12)
      - Conference Introducing Our TV Workshop Color Equipment (Box 12)
      - Annual Meeting of NOAB address (Box 12)
      - New Emphasis on Marketing, Public Relations Counsel, American Bankers Association (Box 12)
      - Seven Areas of Opportunity, Association of National Advertisers (Box 12)
      - Executive Council of American Bankers Association remarks (Box 12)
      - Magazine in Changing America, Magazine Publishers Association (Box 12)
      - Publishers' Weekly, Publishers' Adclub Advertising Awards luncheon comments (Box 12)
      - Look into the Future of Marketing, Harvard Business School Association (Box 12)
    - Vol. IV, 1958 (Box 13)
      - Comments at L.P. Brown alumni rally address, Olympia High School (Box 13)
      - Executive Committee Meeting of NOAB, comments (Box 13)
      - Comments at 11th Annual Reunion Ford Merchandising School (Box 13)
      - As Banking Goes to Market, Annual Convention of Financial Public Relations Association (Box 13)
      - Advertising as a Career, Rochester Advertisers (Box 13)
      - Comments at Reader's Digest sales meeting (Box 13)
      - Four Dimensions of the Customer, National Wholesale Druggists Association (Box 13)
      - Address to Utah Automobile Dealers Association (Box 13)
      - Response at J.D.A. awards dinner (Box 13)
    - Vol. V, 1959
      - Presentation comments, Printer's Ink Gold Medal Award for 1958 (Box 13)